Guide to the Boswell Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
RELATED FAMILIES: DESCENDANTS OF JAMES BOSWELL (1675-1749)
Montgomeries
-----Veronica Boswell (b. 1704?) m. David Montgomerie of Lainshaw
----------* Margaret Montgomerie (ca. 1738-1789) m. 1769 James Boswell
----------James Montgomerie (d. 1766) m. Jean Maxwell
----------*Elizabeth Montgomerie (d. 1776) m. Capt. Alexander Montgomerie-Cuminghame
--------------------------------------------2m. John Beaumont
----------*Mary Montgomerie (d. 1777) m. 1768? James Campbell of Treesbank (d. 1776)
---------------George James Campbell (b. 1768)
---------------David Campbell (b. 1771)
----------Elizabeth Montgomerie (d. 1776) m. Sir Alexander Montgomerie-Cuninghame
---------------Sir Walter Montgomerie-Cuninghame m.
--------------------* Jessie Jane Montgomerie-Cuninghame m. Sir James Boswell (1807-1857)
John Boswell Branch
-----Dr. John Boswell (1710-1780) m. 1742 Anne Cramond (1710-1777)
----------Robert Boswell (1746-1801)
----------James Boswell (1744-1767)
----------Bruce Boswell (1747-1807) m. Mary Lindsay (b. 1755)
----------Alexander Boswell (d. 1783)
----------Elizabeth Boswell (1743-1807)
----------Anne Cramond Boswell (1753-1821)
----------Euphemia Pauline Boswell "died in infancy"
----------Margaret Boswell "died young"
-----Robert Boswell (1746-1801) m. Sibella Sandeman
----------Anne Boswell (1772-1837) m. 1810 Alexander Carre
----------Mary Boswell (1774-1859) m. 1800 William Roxburgh
----------Elizabeth Boswell (1776-1861) m. 1809 John Robert Anderson
----------Alexander Boswell (1781-1850) m. Mary Sandeman (1785-1865)
----------Margaret Catherine Boswell (1785-1877)-----m. 1807 Major-Gen. Nicholas Carnegie
----------John Boswell (1770-1772)
----------Sibella Boswell (b. 1777) "died young"
----------Robert Bruce Boswell (1783-1791)
----------*William Boswell (d. 1841) m. 1799 Elizabeth Boswell (1780-1814)
----------Sibella Boswell (1787-1833) m. 1807 William Egerton
----------Jane Boswell (1789-1769) m. 1811 Henry St. George Tucker
----------Veronica Boswell (1791-1840)
----------John James Boswell (1793-1839) m. Anna Mary Wellwood
----------John Campbell Boswell (1796-1841) m. Elizabeth Leith
-----*William Boswell (d. 1841) m. 1799 Elizabeth Boswell (1780-1814)
----------James Paoli Boswell (1802-1821)
----------Elizabeth Margaret Montgomerie Boswell (1803-after 1873) m. John Williams
----------Bruce Boswell (1805-1855) m. Anne Tronson
----------Sibella Boswell (1806-1807)
----------Robert Cramond Boswell (1807?-1823)
----------William Boswell (1809-1809)
----------Alexander Boswell (1809-1809)
----------Elizabeth Frances Boswell (1810-1812)
----------Annie Boswell (1812-1813)
RELATED FAMILIES: DESCENDANTS OF ALEXANDER BOSWELL, LORD AUCHINLECK (1707-1782)
-----Thomas David Boswell (1748-1826) m. 1783 Anne Catherine Green
----------Maria Boswell
----------Thomas Alexander Boswell (d. 1852) m. Jane Maria Barker
---------------Thomas Charles William Boswell (d. at 18)
BRUCE-KINCARDINE FAMILY
-----Sir George Bruce (d. 1625) m. Margaret Primrose
----------George Bruce (d. 1643) m. Mary Preston of Valleyfield
----------Alexander Bruce, of Alva (d. 1638?)
----------Robert Bruce of Broomhall (d. 1652) m. Helen Skene
----------Anne Bruce m. 1641? Sir James Arnot
----------Magdalen Bruce m. Sir John Erskine
----------Christian Bruce m. Laurence Mercer of Aldie
----------Nicola Bruce (d. 1671) m. Sir John Morrison of Dawsie
----------------------------------2m. John Dick of Braid
----------Margaret Bruce (d. 1652) m. Francis Nicholls
-----George Bruce (d. 1643) m. Mary Preston of Valleyfield
----------Edward Bruce, 1st E. of Kincardine (d. 1662)
----------Alexander Bruce, 2nd E. of Kincardine (ca. 1630-1681) m. 1659
----------Veronica van Aerssen van Sommelsdyck (ca. 1633-1701)
----------Magdalen Bruce m. Sir John Arnot
----------Mary Bruce m. 1655 David Erskine, Lord Cardross
-----Alexander Bruce, 2nd E. (ca. 1630-1680) m. 1659 Veronica van Aerssen van Sommelsdyck (ca. 1633-1701)
----------Charles, Lord Bruce (1660-1680)
----------Alexander, 3rd E. (ca. 1666-1705)
----------Mary Bruce m. ca. 1681 William Cochrane of Ochiltree (d. after 1716)
----------Anne Bruce (d. 1705) m. 1684 Sir David Murray of Stanhope
----------* Elizabeth Bruce (1673-1734) m. 1704 James Boswell of Auchinleck (1672-1749)
COCHRANE FAMILY
-----William Cochrane of Ochiltree (d. after 1727) m.1681 Lady Mary Bruce (d. after 1739)
----------Charles Cochrane of Ochiltree (1683-1752)
----------Alexander Cochrane (1686-1708)
----------George Cochrane (1689-1709)
----------Major-General James Cochrane (1690-1758) m. [Margaret Hawkison?]
----------Thomas Cochrane m. 1721 Elizabeth Ker
------------------------------2m. 1744 Jean Stuart
----------Euphemia Cochrane (1693?-1721) m. Lieut.-Col. John Erskine (1660-1737)
----------John Cochrane (1694-1707)
----------Basil Cochrane (1701-1788)
----------Anne Cochrane (d. 1779) m. 1725 Sir George Preston of Valleyfield (d. 1719)
-----Euphemia Cochrane (1693?-1721) m. Lieut.-Col. John Erskine (1660-1737)
----------Mary Erskine (1715-1766) m. Rev. Alexander Webster (1707-1784)
----------Elizabeth Erskine (1717-after 1759)
Appendix II: Glossary of Scots and Legal Terminology
This glossary has been compiled from several sources, including the Oxford English Dictionary and John Dalrymple's Essay Toward a General History of Feudal Property. It is not intended to be a complete list of Scottish words or feudal law terminology, and the definitions are not exhaustive. Rather, it is a guide to some of the unfamiliar words appearing frequently in the papers of the Boswell Collection.
backbond A document by which a person receiving or holding a seemingly absolute title to property acknowledges that he is actually holding it in trust for a specified reason, and binds himself to return it or account for it after that purpose is served. The true owner of the property is usually the grantor of the absolute deed and the grantee of the backbond.
barony In Scotland, a large freehold estate, almost always held directly from the King; the owner is called the laird, which is not a title of nobility but "goes with" the land.
bond Generally, a legal document by which a person binds himself, his heirs, executors, or assigns to pay another person or his representatives a sum of money. There are many types of bonds in Scottish law, including the backbond and the heritable bond.
cain, kain Rent payment in kind made by tenants to a feudal superior.
clare constat Latin for "It is clearly established," meaning that the feudal superior is satisfied that his late vassal died enfeoffed in the land, and that the person claiming entry into his estate is the nearest lawful heir. A precept of clare constat is a deed executed by a superior in order to complete the title of his vassal's heir to the lands held by the dead vassal.
composition Specialized meaning: fee paid to be admitted as a burgess.
dispone To make over or assign property legally and formally, usually by means of a disposition.
distreyne Distrain: to seize goods or property in order to enforce payment of debt.
dittay Statement of legal charges.
entry Entry into possession or occupation of lands, especially the act of taking possessing of lands by setting foot on them ("entering" them.) See also non-entries.
escheat In English feudal law, the lapsing of land to the Crown on the death of an intestate tenant or owner without heirs. In Scottish law, escheat has a wider sense, including confiscation or forfeiture of property at law (e.g. upon conviction of treason). A simple escheat is an absolute forfeiture; a liferent escheat is forfeiture of all profits accumulated during the forfeited person's lifetime.
excambion Exchange or barter, particularly of land
feu Estate in land held on condition of homage and service to a superior lord, by whom it is granted and in whom ownership remains (English fee). Or, a feudal tenure of land in which the vassal substitutes an amount of grain or money for military service. In modern usage, a perpetual lease at a fixed rent.
feu simple Estate in land which belongs to the owner and his heirs perpetually, not limited to any particular class of heirs.
fiar Owner of the feu simple of a property. See also: life-rent.
fiars The annually fixed prices of different kinds of grains.
grassum Fine paid to a feudal superior when making entry into a feu.
heritable bond Bond for a sum of money, the security for which is a conveyance of land out of heritage to be held by the creditor until the debt is paid. A heritable security is usually created by enfeoffing the creditor in the lands conditionally, i.e. in case of non-payment. Many of the title transfers in Land Purchases and Land Records are actually executions of Heritable bonds and/or backbonds.
heritors Literally, owners of heritable property; usually refers to men who owe the "parish" or "public" burdens (minister's salary, road taxes, etc.).
horning Outlawing. By the seventeenth century, an action against a delinquent debtor issued under the signet, charging him to pay or "be put to the horn" (declared rebel).
intromit To interfere with property belonging to another person.
laird A Scottish landowner who holds land directly from the Crown; a tenant-in-chief of the King. Not a title of personal nobility. A laird is referred to by the name of his holding; the current holder of Auchinleck is referred to as Auchinleck.
liferent Income a person is entitled to receive for life, or the right to receive that income. Often granted in marriage provisions for widows; usually reserved by the holder of a feu if he transfers title to the feu itself before his death.
mail Payment, fee.
mains The "main" farm of an estate, usually farmed by the laird directly rather than feued.
master In the phrase "Master of" followed by the name of a land holding (e.g. "Master of Auchinleck"): the eldest son and heir presumptive of the laird of that land.
non-entry Failure of an heir to enter land and to obtain investiture in it from his feudal superior. Non-entries are the feudal fines arising from this failure. Most often seen as a "gift of the non-entries" (i.e., a remission of the fines) by a superior to the heir.
outquyt To free lands from a wadset by paying the debts upon them.
poind To seize and sell the goods of a delinquent debtor. Usually seen as part of a "writ of horning and poinding," ordering the debtor to make restitution or to be declared outlaw and forfeit his goods.
progress In progress of the writs, means "such a series of title- deeds of a landed estate as is sufficient in law to constitute a valid and effectual title thereto." The best documentation consists of sasines and charters, but many other types of legal instruments may be found in them.
rase, raise To draw up a legal summons, letter, etc.
resignation Form by which holder of a feu returns it to the hands of the feudal superior and/or transfers title of a heritable feu to the next heir.
retour See service.
reversion Obligation by a creditor which allows that his debtor may redeem land in which he had enfeoffed the creditor as security. Usually found in combination with heritable bonds, backbonds, and/or wadsets.
roup Auction.
sasine As a verb, the act of giving possession of feudal property. An instrument of sasine is the legal document that records and proves a transfer of property, and is the decisive proof of ownership in Scottish law. After 1614 all sasines were required to be registered in the Book of Sasines.
service Procedure for determining who is the heir to a dead person. A general service determines who is the heir to someone generally, while a special service discovers the heir to a particular estate. A retour is the report of the inquest in a particular service, with the jury's verdict, and these are either general or special also.
sucken The group of tenants in thirlage to a particular mill, required to bring their grain to it and to keep it in repair.
tack Lease for a specified period of time. Usually applied to farms and land property, but liferents, teinds, and other forms of income can also be leased.
tailzie An entail, binding the descent of a property through a specified line of heirs.
teinds Tithes. Originally owed to parish churches, after the Reformation the right to collect these was often sold to the heritors of the parish or other notables. The 1633 Act of Teinds was an attempt to regularize the situation.
thirlage Being bound, as a tenant, to bring one's grain to the landlord's mill and to keep that mill in repair.
tocher Dowry agreements and the dowry itself.
towst Tax or other impost.
wadset Type of mortgage in which title to land is conveyed as security for a debt, with an explicit reservation of power by the debtor to recover the lands if the debt is paid (usually within a specified period).
writer Counterpart of the English "solicitor." Lawyer who can advise clients and prepare causes, but who is not allowed to present them at the Bar.
w.s. Abbreviation for "writer to the Signet," the highest classification of writers.
Conventicle act, 1670; Administration of estates -- Scotland; Agriculture -- Economic aspects -- Scotland; Authors, English -- Biography; Church lands -- Scotland; Consanguinity; Dissenters, Religious; English literature -- Scottish authors; English literature -- 18th century; Entail -- Scotland; Family archives -- Scotland; Farm management -- Scotland -- Records and correspondence; Inheritance and succession -- Scotland; Land tenure -- Scotland; Landlord and tenant -- Scotland; Law -- Great Britain; Law -- Scotland; Manors -- Scotland; Marriage -- Scotland; Patronage, Political -- Great Britain; Presbyterian Church -- Scotland; Quietism -- Scotland; Religious poetry, English -- Scotland; Women -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Scotland; Women -- Scotland -- Social conditions; Ayrshire (Scotland); Great Britain -- Economic conditions -- 18th century; Great Britain -- History -- 1660-1714; Great Britain -- Intellectual life -- 18th century; Great Britain -- Politics and government -- 1660-1688; Great Britain -- Religion -- 17th century; Great Britain -- Rural conditions; Great Britain -- Social life and customs -- 18th century; Scotland -- Church history -- 17th century; Scotland -- Economic conditions; Scotland -- History -- Sources; Scotland -- History -- 1660-1688; Family papers; Authors; Biographers; Lawyers; Abercrombie, James, 1758-1841; Alleyn, Edward, 1566-1626; Argyll, Archibald Campbell, Earl of, 1629-1685; Auchinleck, Alexander Boswell, Lord, 1707-1782; Baretti, Giuseppe, 1719-1789; Beattie, James, 1735-1803; Beauclerk, Topham, 1739-1780; Blair, Hugh, 1718-1800; Boswell, Alexander, Sir, 1775-1822; Boswell, James, Sir, 1807-1857; Boswell, James, 1740-1795; Boswell, James, 1778-1822; Boswell, Margaret Montgomerie, -1789; Boswell, Thomas David; Bowles, William, 1762-1850; Burke, Edmund, 1729-1797; Burnet, Gilbert, 1643-1715; Burney, Charles, 1726-1814; Burney, Fanny, 1752-1840; Charles, King of England, II, 1630-1685; Charrière, Isabelle de, 1740-1805; Dalrymple, David, Sir, 1726-1792; Davies, Thomas, 1713-1785; Dempster, George, 1732-1818; Devonshire, William Cavendish, Duke of, 1640-1707; Dundas, Robert; Erskine, Andrew, 1739-1793; Forbes, William, Sir, 1739-1806; Garrick, David, 1717-1779; Goldsmith, Oliver, 1730?-1774; Hamilton, David, Sir, 1663-1721; Hog, James, 1658?-1734; Hume, David, 1711-1776; James, King of England, II, 1633-1701; Johnson, Samuel, 1709-1784; Johnston, John, 1729?-1786; Kames, Henry Home, Lord, 1696-1782; Kincardine, Alexander Bruce, Earl of, d. 1681; Langton, Bennet, 1737-1801; Lauderdale, Elizabeth Murray Maitland, Duchess of, -1697; Lauderdale, John Maitland, Duke of, 1616-1682; Lofft, Capel, 1751-1824; Lonsdale, James Lowther, Earl of, 1736-1802; Loudoun, John Campbell, Earl of, 1705-1782; Malone, Edmond, 1741-1812; Oglethorpe, James, 1696-1785; Paoli, Pasquale, 1725-1807; Percy, Thomas, 1729-1811; Piozzi, Hester Lynch, 1741-1821; Pringle, John, Sir, 1707-1782; Reynolds, Joshua, Sir, 1723-1792; Rousseau, Jean-Jacques, 1712-1778; Seward, Anna, 1742-1809; Sheridan, Thomas, 1719-1788; Voltaire, 1694-1778; Warton, Joseph, 1722-1800; Warton, Thomas, 1728-1790; Wilkes, John, 1725-1797; Auchinleck (parish) -- Scotland; Melrose Abbey -- Scotland; Temple, William Johnston, 1739-1796
- Letters, 1761-1795; Series I; 2.75; (7 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Letters, consists of letters by James Boswell arranged alphabetically by name of recipient and housed in Boxes 1-7.
  - Galleys (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Abercrombie, James (L 1-3), 1792-94 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Adams, Sarah (L 5), 1786 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Adams, William (L 6-8), 1778-85 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Adey, Mary (L 9), 1785 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agar, Welbore Ellis (L 10-12), 1791-95 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Agnew, Nathaniel (L 13), 1772 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alexander, Claud (L 15-15.4), 1787-94 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Allegranza, Giuseppe (L 16), 1765 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ambler, William (L 16.2), 1789 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ashbury, Francis (L 18), 1767 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Astle, Daniel (L 19), 1786-87 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Auchinleck Session (L 20.5), 1792 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baden-Durlach, Karl Friedrich, Margrave of (L 21-25), 1764-66 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Barber, Francis (L 28-29), 1786-87 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Baretti, Giuseppe (L 30, 32), 1765, 1769 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Barnard, Frederick Augusta (L 34), 1790 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Barnard, Thomas, Bishop of Killaloe (L 35-50), 1781-92 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
  - Bassi, Laura Maria Catherina (L 51), 1765 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Beattie, James (L 52-54), 1772-80 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Beauclerk, Lady Diana (L 55), 1781 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Beauclerk, Topham (L 56), 1775 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Beckett, Oliver (L 57), 1792 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Blair, Hugh (L 59-62.2), 1777 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bolton, James Clayton (L 63), 1786 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Borgaretto, Vittoria Enrichetta, Countess of (L 64-67), 1765 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bosville, William (L 68-70), 1784, 1788 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Boswell, Alexander, Lord Auchinleck (L 71), [1775?] (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Boswell, Sir Alexander (L 73-124), 1786-95 (Box 1, Folder 20-26)
  - Boswell, Christoph Leopold and August Ferdinand von (L 125), 1791 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Boswell, Elizabeth, Lady Auchinleck (L 126), 1791 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Boswell, Euphemia Erskine, Lady Auchinleck (L 127), 1754 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Boswell, Euphemia (L 128), 1790 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Boswell, James (the younger) (L 129-160), 1793-95 (Box 1, Folder 28-33)
  - Boswell, Dr. John (L 161), 1768 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Boswell, John (L 162), 1779 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Boswell, John, of Knockroon (L 162.4), 1793 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Boswell, Margaret Montgomerie (L 166-193), 1767-89 (Box 2, Folder 35-41)
  - Boswell, Robert (L 196-260), 1775-94, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42-52)
  - Boswell, Veronica (L 262-263.1), 1781-90 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Bowles, William (L 264-265, 268), 1785-87 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Boyd, Jane (L 269), 1769 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Brocklesby, Richard (L 272), 1784 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Buchanan, Mrs. (L 309-310), 1789-90 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Burgoyne, John (L 311, 313), 1778-90 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Burke, Edmund (L 314-335), 1785-91 (Box 2, Folder 57-59)
  - Burke, Richard (L 336), 1785 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Burney, Charles (L 336.5-337.3), 1787-92 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Bute, John Stuart, 3rd D. of (L 339-343), 1781 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Bute, John Stuart, 4th E. of (L 344-349), 1766-93 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Campbell, (Amelia Ramsay), Lady (L 350), 1791 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Campbell, Bruce (L 351-352), 1782-88 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Campbell, John (L 353), 1775 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Campbell, Rev. John (L 354), 1793 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Carlisle, Frederick Howard, 5th E. of (L 355), 1789 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Cator, John (L 356), 1792 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Catt, Henri de (L 357-358), 1764 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Chalmer, James (L 359-360), 1782-86 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Chalmers, Margaret (L 361), 1783 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Chambers, (Frances Wilton), Lady (L 362), 1795 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Chapman, Joseph (L 363), 1786 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Chatham, William Pitt, 1st E. of (L 364-368), 1766-67 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - (including Tinker 305) Churton, Ralph (L 369-370), 1792-93 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Cobb, Mary (Hammond) (L 372-375), 1784-89 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Coloquhoun, Catherine (L 376), 1761 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Coombe, Thomas (L 378), 1790 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Cooper, Allen (L 379), 1792 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Cornwallis, Charles Cornwallis, 2nd E and 1st M. (L 380), 1774 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Cosway, Maria (L 381-384), 1785-95 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Courtenay, John (L 385-389), 1785 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Covington, Alexander Lockhart, Lord (L 390), 1786 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Crawford, Jean (Hamilton), Countess of (L 393-395), 1779-90 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Croft, Herbert (L 396-397), 1784-85 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Crosbie, Andrew (L 398), 1774 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Cummyng, James (L 399), 1785 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Cuninghame, Sir William (L 399.6), 1794 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - [Dalrymple, William?] (L 401.5), 1793 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Dance, Nathaniel (L 403), 1765 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Davies, Thomas (L 404), 1780 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Dawson, Alexander (L 405), 1790 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - De Coetlogon, Charles Edward (L 408), 1793 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - DeLaval, John Hussey (L 409-410), 1795 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Deleyre, Alexandre (L 411-413), 1765-66 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Dempster, George (L 414-423), 1761-91 (Box 3, Folder 75-76)
  - Denis, Louise (L 424), 1764 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Dick, Sir Alexander (L 424.6-425), 1777-84 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Dick, Sir John (L 426-428), 1786-90 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Dick, Sir William (L 429), 1780 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Dilly, Charles (L 430), 1779 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Divry, Mlle. (L 432-433), 1791 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Douglas, Archibald James Edward Douglas, 1st Baron of Douglas (L 434-436), 1779-87 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Douglas, Joanna (L 437), 1785 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Douglas, John, Bishop of Salisbury (L 438-440), 1787-91 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Douglas, Margaret (Douglas) Duchess of (L 441), 1766 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Dreghorn, (John Maclaurin), Lord (L 442-443.1), 1782-91 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Drummond, George Home (L 444), 1786 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Dumfries, Patrick Macdowell-Crichton, 5th E. of (L 445), 1783 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Dun, Alexander Boswell (L 446), 1792 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Dun, John (L 446.5), 1792 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Dundas, Henry (L 447-479), 1780-94 (Box 3, Folder 83-86)
  - Dundas, Lady Jane (Hope) (L 480), 1793 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Dundas, Robert (L 481-484), 1767-82 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Dundas, Robert ("Young Arniston") (L 485), 1794 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Dunlop, Frances Anne (L 485.5), 1793 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Eardley, Selena (L 486), 1792 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Edinburgh Defensive Band (L 487), 1782 (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Eglinton, Archibald Montgomerie, 11th E. of (L 493-498), 1781-93 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Eglinton, Hugh Montgomerie, 12th E. of (L 499), 1781 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Elford, William (L 500), 1792 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Elibank, Patrick Murray, 5th Lord (L 501), 1773 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Eliot, Edward Craggs-Eliot, 1st B. of St. Germans (L 502), 1791 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Elphinston, James (L 503), 1791 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Elphinstone, John Elphinstone, 11th Lord (L 504), 1785 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Errol, James Hay, 15th Lord (L 505), 1774 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Erskine, Andrew (L 506-531), 1761-93 (Box 3, Folder 92-95)
  - Erskine, Henry (L 532.2), 1790 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Erskine, John (L 532.3), 1793 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Exeter, Brownlow Cecil, 9th E. of (L 533), 1792 (Box 3, Folder 96)